Okay, I got the red smoke.
>> GUN RUN, NORTH OR SOUTH, WEST OF THE
SMOKE, WEST OF THE SMOKE.
>> OKAY, COPY. West of the smoke. I'm
looking at danger close now.
>> Come on, WHAT IS IT? GIVE IT TO ME. I
NEED IT.
YOU'RE CLEARED HOT.
>> COPY, cleared hot.
>> It's been It's been fascinating to watch
your journey over the last couple years.
>> It's been kind of like that.
>> Well, that's I think just life.
>> Um
I was thinking about I was
really looking forward to sitting down
and talking with you. We originally
obviously linked up over a Change Agents
episode. They had a full page of
production notes. I don't think I even
asked you a single question cuz we just
started talking about other stuff from
like the global war on terror time.
>> It was fantastic. And then I was like,
"Oh my god, we have to get this person
in person."
And uh I was thinking about it.
I have I have to ask a question
tangential to your old job based off of
my understanding of the agency based off
of movies.
>> Mhm.
>> I love the movie Charlie Wilson's War.
>> Oh.
>> And I heard you talking one time about a
particular character in that movie and I
am hoping
>> Yep.
>> that you actually got to work with this
person and
Yes.
>> is my mentor.
>> Okay.
>> And one of my closest friends.
>> Did he actually break somebody's office
glass with a hammer or wrench?
>> Oh, he used his fist.
>> [laughter]
>> First of all, and I'll tell you what,
they they sort of eased off in the movie
because in the movie the the window that
he was breaking was the division chief.
Which is a career ending
>> 100%.
>> In real life, it was the Deputy Director
for Operations.
>> Oh, boy.
>> Of the whole CIA.
>> So, it was the boss's boss.
>> I said, "How did they not take you out
in handcuffs?"
I asked him one time.
and he said, "Everybody's afraid of me
because they think I'm crazy."
And there's something to be said about
that. He His nickname at the agency,
we're talking about Gus Avrakotos who
was played by Philip Seymour Hoffman in
the film Charlie Wilson's War.
>> spectacular actor as well.
>> Oh, what?
They could not have found a more perfect
actor.
>> Did he Did he nail it pretty well?
>> Um no, Gus Gus was far filthier than
[laughter] uh
>> So, this is the point where
>> the reality of it wouldn't even have
been made.
>> Was he as much of a legend as he came
off to be in that movie?
>> Yes.
>> That is unbelievable.
>> Yes. And you know, I'll tell you
well, I could tell you a lot about Gus.
His nickname was Dr. Dirty and I said to
him one time
I said, "Why Dr. Dirty? I've found you
to be anything but dirty."
And he said
"Cuz I'll stab you in the back just like
everybody else in this building will,
but
then I'm going to spin you around and
stab you in the front."
>> [laughter]
>> Was he like a Was he just a spy spy?
>> Yeah. He was a mean son of a [__]
>> Is that what they're looking for? Did
that place turn him into that or was
that just who he was?
>> No, that's what that was the draw to
bring him in. I'll tell you why he was
so unique.
And he was very, very proud of this.
He came into the agency
in those early days when everybody was
coming from Harvard, Yale, Dartmouth,
Brown, Princeton.
And he was from Pitt. He had a degree in
Soviet studies from Pitt.
And he was kind of an ethnic, you know,
full-blooded Greek from from Aliquippa,
Pennsylvania, which was another reason
why we hit it off.
I I went into operational training at
the sort of halfway point in my career.
And um
and he says to me, "Eselinas, are you
Greek?" And I said, "Yeah." Apropos, he
said, "Where are you from? Where's your
family from?" And he said, "Over from I
think it was Sparta." Which makes sense.
And um so we started talking. And I
said, "You You speak with a Pittsburgh
accent. You from Pittsburgh?"
And he said, "Yeah, I'm from Aliquippa.
You?" And I said, "Yeah, I'm from New
Castle. Go Steelers, right?" And I
pulled out my Steelers credit card that
I still have in my pocket. Right?
[laughter]
Yeah, I got my There it is. I should
probably cover up the numbers totally.
But uh
yeah, my Steelers credit card. So, we
hit it off on the very first day. So, he
got
me assigned to him
um as
his
student, his underling.
>> As you switched over to operations?
>> As I switched over to operations. And
the cool thing about that was I was
already mid-career. Everybody in the
class was mid-career. It was called the
operations course accelerated, OCA.
And so
if you are just joining the CIA and
you're going into operations, you got to
go to this desk for 6 months
>> Yeah.
>> and learn what that desk does. And then
you go to this office for 6 months or 6
weeks or whatever and learn what they
do. We didn't need any of that stuff cuz
we'd already been in for
6, 8, 10 years.
So, we went straight into ops. And um
he used to say, "The job of an
operations officer is to recruit spies
to steal secrets. That's what you're
going to learn to do here. Recruit spies
to steal secrets."
And um
you know, one of the things that I
remember about him in training was that
the other trainers didn't like him.
>> Hm.
>> And some [clears throat] of them were
like openly rude to him. And he just
took it. And I said I said, "Why are
these [__] so mean to you?" And he's
like, "Mean? That doesn't even The word
doesn't even register in my brain. You
want to see mean? You get to know me,"
he says.
>> Hm.
>> And I thought, "That's kind of cool."
I'll tell you another thing about Gus.
Gus was incredibly generous
to me with his time and his expertise.
So, I finished the class. I go out to
Athens in counterterrorism. And
as good as that would kind of silly, we
had just gotten this newfangled thing
called electronic mail, right? E-mail.
So,
>> I remember this when this occurred as
well, too. It was
Something I have to tell my children,
but they're like, "What are you talking
about? That existed forever." I'm like
>> were all like gathered around the
computer like and I remember she says,
"Wait a minute. Wait a minute. Are you
saying that my people can just write one
of these e-mails
and it goes back to somebody at
headquarters and then that person can
respond?" And the tech guy says, "Yeah."
And he goes, "I don't like it. I don't
like it one bit."
>> [laughter]
>> So, I don't worry, sir. One day the
agency will develop the ability to read
everybody. So, it's [laughter] going to
be fine.
>> Imagine.
So, which came like a year later.
>> Oh, I can only imagine. Yeah.
>> So,
Gus and I he was the very first email I
sent. So, I said, "Gus, just arrived in
Athens. Just wanted you know I'm in
place." And he was like, "Great. Let's
talk every day. Great." So, we would do
things like
I got to be look I got I got to be
careful. So, I'm going to tell you one
thing. [laughter] I said, "Gus." I
emailed him one day. I said, "Gus,
there's there's a a guy just arrived
here. And this guy has got to be like
target number one for me."
But, he's from this
outcast country. So, he's not showing up
at the diplomatic cocktail parties. How
do I get this guy? I just got to get in
front of him. I know he's not going to
accept a pitch, but I want to scare the
[__] out of him is what I want to do.
And he's like, "You know what? I did
something in the Middle East once
back in '68 or what it what it whatever
the year was.
Here's what you do.
And I even say in my first book I wish I
had thought of it because it was so
brilliant. It was so simple. So
brilliant. What I did, I looked much
younger then. I was 35
years old. Didn't have any gray hair.
And um
and I loaded a a book bag uh like a gym
bag full of books.
And I went to this guy's house.
He lived in a very close-in suburb. And
uh I knew what car
was his. And so I took my book bag and I
broke the side view mirror off of his
car.
Just broke it, snapped it right off.
Then I picked it up and I went to his
next door neighbor's house.
A Greek lady. Oh, sorry.
Greek lady.
>> [laughter]
>> And um and I said to her
"Is this your car? I I I broke this off
by accident." And she says, "No, no,
it's not my car. It's the guy next
door."
Um and she says to me, "Then he ain't an
alien cuz he's not Greek." I was like,
"Okay, sorry. Thank you. Sorry to bother
you." So I go next door and knock on the
guy's door.
He answers the door and I said "Uh messi
koulieta kiria laspasa to jamis as."
He's like, "Wait a minute. Wait a
minute. I don't speak Greek."
I said, "Oh, you speak English?" He
said, "Yeah." I said, "Oh, I speak
English, too." I said, "Sir, I was
walking down the street and my bag
accidentally got caught on the mirror
and I broke the mirror off and the lady
next door told me that it was your car
and I wanted to say how sorry I was and
I wanted to I want to pay for it." He's
like, "Oh,
man, now
now I got to take it to the shop and
it's all nothing but trouble." I said,
"I am so sorry. Please allow me to pay
for it."
"May I have a glass of water?"
In his culture
you can't decline a request for
hospitality.
And he goes
>> [sighs]
>> "Wait right here."
Well, I could see
inside the house his little girl was
playing on the on the carpet. She looked
to be about four.
So, I I walked inside the house.
And I get down on my knees and I said to
her, uh,
"Shu ismik?" What is your name? In
Arabic.
"Shu ismik?" And she said, "My name is
Miriam." And I said, "How old are you,
Miriam?" "I'm four."
He comes back in with the water.
And, uh, and he says to me, "What
exactly do you want?"
>> [laughter]
>> And I said, "I'm not going to insult
you.
I'm from the CIA in Washington. I know
who you are. I know what you do here.
And I'm here to tell you that
your leader,
he's going to die.
You can die with him
or you can come on the side of the good
guys. And I'm not going to ask twice.
You have until 10:00 tomorrow morning to
make your decision." I said, "This is my
business card. It's my true name."
10:00.
And I set it down.
And I'm looking at him. And he says, "I
admire your courage in approaching me.
Very creative.
But I'm offended that you would do it in
my own home in front of my child."
And I said,
"My apologies."
And I walked out.
>> Today's episode is brought to you by
Black Rifle Coffee.
Spring is a reset. Longer days, more
visibility, no more hiding behind winter
habits. Out with the excuses, in with
discipline.
Black Rifle Coffee didn't adopt grit
when it became marketable. They were
founded on it by veterans who understand
that courage is consistency. It's
showing up early. It's doing the reps no
one sees. If you want simple and strong,
start with just black. Whole bean if you
run the grinder, ground if you keep it
straightforward, pods if efficiency
matters. No trendy flavor experiments,
no sugar masking weak beans, just bold
American roasted coffee that does its
job every single morning. And if you
want rotation without sacrificing
backbone, the supply drop variety pack
delivers. A lineup of pod roast designed
to keep you sharp while maintaining
standards, different profiles, same
mission.
This isn't lifestyle branding, it's
daily discipline in a cup. New season,
new expectations, higher bar.
You can grab just black or the supply
drop variety pack on Amazon or go direct
to blackriflecoffee.com
and have it shipped straight to your
door. Black Rifle Coffee, veteran
founded, American roasted, stay
deliberate, keep the standard high.
>> The next morning, everybody's gathered
around my phone. We're all just sitting
there looking at the phone like 1 minute
to 10. It rings and I was like
[laughter]
I knew I scared him. I knew I scared
him.
And so he said, I've given your offer
some thought. When can we meet? I said,
in 2 hours
at such and such a hotel. The lobby had
a coffee shop.
We We had every table. We took every
table. Every table had an armed CIA
officer there.
And I said, come alone and come unarmed.
And he came alone and I got up, I gave
him a big bear hug to make it look
normal and I patted him down for
weapons. He was unarmed and he sat down
and asked me what I wanted. I was very
specific with what I wanted and I said,
what do you want? He said, what are you
offering?
I said, relocation if you want it.
I mean, not not tomorrow.
We're We're going to have some work to
do, but
if you want to move to the United
States.
He didn't. He wanted to move to another
Arab country.
Uh which was fine. We gave him a
more money than one person can carry at
a time.
And and my station chief came up to me
and he said,
"I've been here for 25 years. This was
the most creative operation I've ever
seen." And this was my first tour. And I
said, "You know, I wish I could take
credit for it."
"What do you mean?" he says. I said,
"Gus told me to do this. It was his
idea."
And he's like, "Fucking Gus." He hated
[laughter] him.
He hated him. And then poor Gus the the
older he got the sicker he got. He
as you might imagine he had a blood
pressure problem.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
>> And that led to a series of mini
strokes. And every time he would have a
mini stroke he would get meaner.
To the point one time
>> personality shift?
>> a personality change.
It got to the point where he somehow got
it into his head that I told somebody
that I had seen him escorted out of the
building with the cops. I said, "What
are you talking about?" "Three weeks ago
you told Alan that" I said, "Gus, I've
been in Pakistan for 6 months.
I don't know what you're talking about.
I just got back from Pakistan a couple
days ago. I haven't seen Alan in years.
I don't know what you're talking about."
But someone actually called security
because the way he was screaming at me
in the hallway.
And mutual friend of ours was like,
"Look, he keeps having these mini
strokes. He's not himself." And then it
got to the point and this is kind of a
sad
sort of ignominious way to end such a
proud career.
He got it into his head that George
Tenet, who was the CIA director at the
time, had denied him
a good parking space.
And he started emailing George.
>> Oh.
>> Yeah, directly. Cuz everybody in the
agency knows George's email address. I
mean, it's
>> [laughter]
>> you know, George Tenet at CIA.gov.
>> Exactly. George.Tenet
>> Exactly. It's not hard to figure out.
It's not like he's an alias or
something. And so he he was like, "You
know, why'd you take away my parking
space? And of course, nobody ever
responded to him, but it got to the
point where tenant finally said,
"It's time for Gus to go."
And that's how his career ended.
>> You know, the worst part about that is
I've been around some people now, um
stroke and also the early onset of
dementia. They don't realize To them,
what they are experiencing is real.
They're their own worst enemy because
they don't see the personality shift and
everybody They think that everybody else
has gone crazy.
>> Yes.
>> Good luck having that conversation with
somebody.
>> right. My dad, God rest his soul, my I
had I had the best dad anybody could
ever hope to have in life. He was a very
gentle soul, PhD in music education, 44
years as an elementary school principal
in the public school system, just a
an all-around good guy.
And he got Parkinson's disease. And
sometimes Parkinson's is also associated
with Parkinsonian dementia.
So, I used to I was working at the
United Nations at the time. My
kids were living in Ohio with my
ex-wife. So, I used to drive either from
Washington or from New York every other
weekend, pick up the kids, go to my mom
and dad's house.
So, my dad had a back surgery, and he
came out of the surgery with something
called hospital psychosis, which is an
actual thing, where if you're already
prone to dementia,
it's the
the stuff that they give you to knock
you out for the surgery. Yeah, the
anesthesia. It it makes you crazy.
>> Oh, that doesn't sound awesome.
>> No. And sometimes you can finally come
out of it over a period of weeks or
months. Sometimes you never come out of
it.
So,
he calls me. I'm in New York. He calls
me at like midnight one night, and he
said, um I need for you to call the
congressman.
I said, "Which congressman?"
"My congressman." I said, "Why?" He
said, "Al-Qaeda was in my my hospital
room and they tried to recruit me." And
I got a tip off the congressman.
But I knew what he was talking about
because that day on the news we had
disrupted FBI disrupted What was the
name of that attack?
Uh Fort something attack in New Jersey.
>> Mhm.
>> Before it took place they grabbed these
six Al-Qaeda guys. So their pictures
were on the news all day that day and he
imagined that they were in the room the
hospital room.
>> Yeah.
>> So he said, "If you don't call the
congressman I'm calling the sheriff." I
said, "Dad,
we're all over these guys.
It's all part of the operation." I said,
"Don't worry about it." He goes, "Oh,
you're out you're on it?" And I said,
"I'm I'm on it like white on rice, Dad."
And then he backed off.
>> You should have told him we need you
though. We need you to be a triple
agent. We need you to go undercover.
>> Yes.
Just be totally silent.
>> Yeah, listen, take notes, tell me
everything. You are the linchpin to this
operation.
>> Yeah. I went to see him at the hospital
that next weekend
and I was with my mom. And my mom and
dad, I say this all the time, they were
deeply in love with each other like all
my life.
And so it was time to leave. It was
like, you know, 9:00 and visiting hours
were over. So he walked with us to the
elevator and then he tried to get into
the elevator. And my mom said, "Honey,
you can't go home with us." And he got
mad and he says, "Stella, that girl at
the hotel told me I could go home
anytime I wanted."
>> [laughter]
>> And she said, "You're not in a hotel,
you're in a hospital."
He got out and he he looks at me and he
says
he says, "Good night, buddy." And I
said, "Good night, Dad." And then he
looks at my mom and he says
I can't even say this straight face
because as for you
I'm done with you.
>> [laughter]
>> She cried all the way home. And I was
like, "Mom, he's not in his right mind.
He can't help it." But then he would
have a good day.
>> Yeah.
>> Then he would have two good days. And
then finally after a while, he snapped
out of it. And he was his normal self
again. And then couldn't believe the
stuff that we were telling him he had
said.
Couldn't believe it.
>> I if I hadn't been around people now who
have experienced that, I wouldn't
believe it either. But now having seen
it,
>> Mhm.
>> what a
How can you win a battle against your
own brain?
>> I don't
know. God. I've got a friend, a very
dear friend, whose dad just passed away
in his 90s.
And he had a stroke. And so his
short-term memory was just gone. Well,
my buddy's brother died in 1991. He was
young. He was in his 20s.
Died in 1991. And every single day his
dad would say, "Where's Billy? I haven't
seen Billy. Why hasn't he come to visit
me?" And every day they had to say,
"Billy died 35 years ago." And then he
would just burst into tears. So finally
they just said, "Billy Billy was just
here 2 hours ago. You don't remember."
"Oh, okay. Okay. When's he coming again?
He's coming tomorrow. Don't worry about
it."
>> I think that's the move.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
But getting [snorts] back to Gus,
Gus was like one of the most one of the
manliest men. I'll tell you what,
and this is what a dear friend he was.
I'll tell you two more Gus things. What
a dear friend he was. I was going
through divorce coming out of Athens.
And I was just
just wrecked.
>> I've been through one myself. I know
what you're talking about.
>> It's bad. I've been through two. The
second one was worse. But the first one
I'm like,
"My life is over at 36." I couldn't
believe it. And he said to me,
I This is going to sound so crude, but
this is just the way This is just the
way Gus used to talk. He says, "Don't
worry about that. You're going to get
more [__] than you've ever had in your
entire life. You're going to have more
[__] than you're going to know what to
do with." I'm like, "Gus, I feel old and
broken and and I'm 20 lb overweight."
And and he said,
"My wife left me when I was stationed in
Athens."
He said, "I was 44 years old. Next thing
I know, I'm on top of a 20-year-old."
And I said I said, [laughter] "Well, how
the heck did you do that?"
Like, you know, share, right? So I can
try to make a comeback.
And he says,
He said, "I said to her one time, 'Why
are you with an old man like me?'"
And she said, "Because guys my age want
to talk about their stereos and you want
to talk about how beautiful my tits
are."
>> I mean, that's not a bad selling point.
>> "Lesson learned, Gus. [laughter]
Thank you."
>> Write that down in the notebook of life.
>> And then one time, this is my last
[snorts] Gus story unless you have
questions.
He He emailed me and he said, "Listen,
I'm going to be out of touch for 10
days. So, keep on keeping on. I'll drop
you a line when I'm back." I'm like,
"Okay."
Figuring
vacation, family, something.
I'm going to meet with a particularly
sensitive source one day and I'm doing a
3-hour surveillance detection route.
And I'm way down south of Athens.
And I make this turn
and as I turn, I happen to turn and look
and there's Gus standing on the street
corner.
>> [laughter]
>> And I was like, "No. No. No. It's my
imagination cuz I've been thinking about
him, right?" And I carry on with the
SDR.
And then
he emails me like four or five days
later, "Hey, I'm back."
So I said I go, "Gus,
by any chance, 4 days ago,
did I see you standing front of the the
steakhouse in Anavissos
And he writes back
Tell anybody and I'll [__] kill you.
>> [laughter]
>> So afterwards when I got home from the
tour I was like
Way back What in the world were you
doing in Glyfada that day? Why didn't
you tell me you were in Athens? We could
have you know met up or had dinner. And
he says he loved the junta the military
dictatorship his fascist dictatorship
which terrorized Greece for 7 years
murdered thousands of people. He was
like this with those guys.
So he said um
And and the dictator the head of the
junta was a guy named uh
Colonel Papadopoulos.
George Papadopoulos and he said you know
I'm I'm Godfather to Papadopoulos's son.
I was like what?
It's like being Godfather to Hitler's
son.
>> Yeah.
>> Right?
>> Not a good look.
>> No. And he says he's MY GODFATHER. I
TAKE OUR religion seriously. I'm like
okay okay. He said well that's why I
didn't tell anybody. They wouldn't
understand. I go Gus I love you and I
don't understand.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. He he made no excuses.
>> The old SDR.
>> Yeah.
>> My wife
um
has no natural sense of direction.
>> Oh my gosh.
>> I We we share life 360.
>> Right. I do too.
>> I will find her we'll talk on the phone.
And she coaches at a jujitsu gym
literally literally one block away down
the alley by the police station.
I know roughly how long it takes to get
from there to where we live.
And we'll have 20 minute conversations
on the phone.
And I'll ask her where the [__] are you?
And she's like oh
I missed the turn just And so I've
taught her the term SDR. I'm like are
you on another SDR? She goes yes I
definitely am. I actually think
that if she was being observed by an
intelligence agency that they would
think she is actually got an exceptional
level of fieldcraft?
She just has no sense of direction
whatsoever. She would accidentally be
confused with somebody with a high level
of tradecraft.
>> [laughter]
>> I I have
>> I'll find her miles on life. I'm like
You're you're 4 miles from where we live
and the gym is three. She's like, "Oh, I
just took a wrong turn. I'm just going
to see where this goes." I'm like, "Oh
my god. GPS.
>> [laughter]
>> They've invented and and they do great
work." John, it's it's
it's less than a dozen turns to get to
our house. I I now I think it's
fantastic because she at first I'm like,
"Oh, you're on an SDR." She's like,
"What does that mean?" I'm like, "Well,
it's a you know, surveillance detection
route this that or the other." And she's
just like, "Yeah, that's what I'm
doing." So now she just goes with it.
She's like, "Oh, hey, I'm on an SDR.
I'll be home in a little bit."
When Gus was training me and we were
doing SDRs, you know, the final phase in
an SDR is called the provocative phase.
Yeah, when you start making the
aggressive left and right turns. Just
crazy. No, no, it's more more
provocative than the aggressive phase.
You're talking about throwing a U-turn?
U-turns, pulling into somebody's
driveway, go the wrong way down a
one-way street. That's to be just 1,000%
sure that you're clean.
But
usually
you know
if you're clean before you get to that
final phase. And the final phase can it
could be two blocks. You know, you don't
have to drive the wrong way down the
one-way street for very long. But
uh
if you realize you're being followed,
you just abort the meeting.
I I never met anybody that ever had to
go into a provocative phase.
I don't know. Cuz it's so provocative
that the conclusion it could draw
attention to your person. Yeah. And the
conclusion would be like, "Oh, he's He's
a an SDR. We got to put a double team on
him. I worked with this woman in
Bahrain. She was a State Department
officer. She was so freaking arrogant.
She had no reason or right to be
arrogant. She was just arrogant.
She had come from Romania.
Had never served in the Middle East
before. I had already been there a year
when she arrived. She replaced a friend
of mine who went on to be a young
ambassador.
And um
She came to the office one day and she
said, "Have you had surveillance here?"
And I said, "No."
"Not a single time." She said, "I had
surveillance last night." I said,
"That's cuz you're the political
officer. They just assume that everybody
who's the political officer is a CIA
officer." And she wasn't.
I said, "What'd you do?"
And she said, "I took them on a
high-speed chase from the top of this
island to the bottom."
And I was like,
"Good for you." Which of course is
exactly the opposite of what you're
supposed to do. Just go about your
normal business. Maybe act normal.
Because then they're going to say, "Oh,
she's just acting normal. She's She went
to the grocery store and she went to the
dry cleaners and then she went home. She
must not be CIA." And then they move on
to the next guy.
She was so provocative
that
literally
every meeting she went to for the next 2
years, she dragged surveillance to. And
as a result, she pulled surveillance off
of me. I never had it. Never.
>> Yeah, I worry about an intelligence
agency seeing my wife driving. They'd be
like, "She is definitely a sleeper cell.
She's constantly looking for It's like,
no, she's not.
>> [laughter]
>> John, did you ever think that your life
was going to look like what it does
right now?
>> Oh, no, no. I can tell you exactly what
I thought my life would look like. My
wife and I used to talk My second wife
and I used to talk about it. She was a
senior CIA officer as well.
Um I believed very firmly that I would
do my my 25 years because I had 5 years
overseas, you can get 30 years pension
after 25.
And then I would um
retire on a Friday, start up the
following Monday with a contractor, do
another 5 years, and live happily ever
after.
You know, we had a I I won a big award
um at the
after the I was a beta operation, big
award, and I used it to buy a piece of
land in the Outer Banks of North
Carolina. I bought a
a third of an acre.
>> You loved it?
>> Loved it. Love I I still love it. It's
so clean and pristine. It's just
wonderful there. So, it was 10 ft above
sea level, four lots back from the
ocean. Perfect. And um
I just thought, well, I'll retire and
we're going to build our house there and
you know, live happily ever after.
And
no such thing happened.
>> How is it even possible for people who
do or did what you did for a living to
have relationships or be married to
somebody who also doesn't work in that
agency?
>> Oh, it's it's not possible. I hate to
say it, but it's just not possible.
>> I mean, cuz I'm assuming there are I
mean, obviously, if you both work there,
I'm assuming things are obviously still
compartmentalized, but I don't know how
you would even bridge that gap.
>> You can't.
>> You'd have to start off with a lie. I'm
assuming the initiation of the
relationship.
>> only thing my first wife knew was that I
worked at the CIA, and that she couldn't
tell anybody that I worked at the CIA.
That was it.
I [snorts] would come home, especially
once I went operational, I would come
home and she'd say,
"How was your day?" I'd say, "Great."
"What did you do?" "Nothing."
"Who'd you see?" "Nobody."
>> Yeah.
>> I'd go, "Okay. Yep." "How was your day?"
"Good." And then the phone would ring at
11:00. I had seven cell phones.
And I had a
They They always give you a bigger house
than you need, because
you need space to entertain, and you
need space for privacy. So, I one of the
little bedrooms I had as a den and I
kept the door locked.
And I had seven cell phones.
Um all burners, all registered to
fictitious names.
And um 11:00 the phone would ring and I
would say, you know,
"Lilac personal shopping." I didn't.
That was from The Sopranos, but you get
the idea.
>> Yep.
>> And um the guy would say, you know,
whatever the code was and I would
respond with my bonafides.
And um like he would say,
"Hey Billy,
uh I just got back uh to town." And I
would say,
"How was your vacation?"
And he would say, you know, "It rained
the whole time I was gone."
That means,
"Meet me at the hotel coffee shop
in 3 hours."
And we we had
previously arranged we we found a I I
was able to identify a 24-hour coffee
shop. So, I would leave at 11:00. And
she'd be like, "What Where are you
going? It's 11:00."
I have a meeting.
You know, just like in The Sopranos. I
got a meeting. I got to make my
collections.
And so, I would do a 3-hour SDR. I would
do the meeting. The meeting would last
an hour or 2 hours. And then I would do
2 hours back to my house, which maybe
gave me an hour to sleep. And then I'd
get up, shave, shower,
go back to the uh to the office and and
work my normal day.
And just hope I didn't have to do the
same thing again that night.
But she was convinced I was cheating on
her.
>> Well, I mean, the how could she not
think that? I mean, the yeah, the
unregularity of the hours and all of
those things.
>> My second wife, though,
I'll give you an example. I I was uh
it was the day I I was leaving Pakistan.
I'd been there 6 months. I was a beta
was behind us. I had complete and total
success in in Pakistan. And she and I
had been um
uh arranging, planning a week-long
vacation in uh Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Neither one of us had ever been to Santa
Fe.
2 hours
before I left for the airport, I get
this cable and it says, "Don't come
home. Instead, go to this other country
because we want you to break into a
house and plant a bug."
And I was like, "Fuck." [laughter]
So, I called her. It's like, "Then can I
go to Santa Fe?" I know, right?
>> [laughter]
>> I called her and I said, "I am so sorry,
but" and then she said, "No, no.
I saw the cable. Go do your break-in.
We'll go to Santa Fe some other time."
So, she understood what the job
entailed. And we we 2 3 months later, we
went to Santa Fe and had a great time.
But she understood.
>> I think that's the only way it could
work for people in your line of work.
Do you think it's possible for agencies
like the CIA to exist and not become
corrupted?
>> No, I don't. That's a great question and
it's an important question. And the
reason why
I don't think it's possible is because
we will never have appropriate
oversight.
Oversight just will never happen. There
was this like golden age, we like to
think, this golden age of congressional
oversight from 1975
until about 1982
>> Mhm.
>> when Iran-Contra started.
Um coming out of the Church Committee,
the Pike Committee, the creation of the
House and Senate Intelligence
Committees, real oversight with giants
sitting on them.
Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Frank Church,
Birch Bayh,
Barry Goldwater, serious people,
heavyweights in 20th century American
politics who who serious about, you
know, the the constitutionally mandated
oversight authority of Congress.
And then that just kind of went away.
And now they're just cheerleaders. I I
got a call from a senator a week ago,
last Friday, and he said, um "Hey, would
you come up to my office? I There are a
couple of issues I want to talk to you
about."
This has happened a few times in the
last 10 years. And I drop everything and
I Anytime a senator calls me,
drop everything and just go straight up
to the to the hill.
And he pierced this notion that I had
of the golden age
from '75 to '82.
So, I said, "Senator, what can I do for
you?" And we had a little chit-chat,
baseball, and he's a baseball fan, so am
I.
I said, "What can I do for you?"
And he said, "I need your help. There
are some documents that I need from
1975,
and I just can't get access to them."
I said, "You're
You're a senator.
You're committee chairman. You should be
the one with the keys to the drawer.
Yeah, just pick up the phone and tell
them, 'Bring Bring the documents by
noon. Have them in my office.'"
He said, "I've been trying that for the
last 7 years.
And they tell me to go fly a kite."
>> What was the topic he was looking for?
>> Well, that's what it was.
He said, "There's a classified annex
to the 1975 report."
>> [snorts]
>> I said, "There can't be. The whole point
of the
1975 report was that it was unclassified
and released to the public." And he
said, "Right.
That's what they want everybody to
believe."
He said, "I found a classified annex."
He said, "They denied for 7 years that
it existed. And then we found it in a
storage area
in the basement of the Senate."
And I said, "And you you can't just open
the box. He said, "No, it's covered with
decades worth of dust and it's sealed
and they will not let me see it." And I
said, "Have you gone to leadership?" And
he said, "Yeah." And leadership said, "I
don't want to get involved in a dispute
between two committee chairmen."
I said, "This is This is outrageous."
And because
they're congressional documents
classified by a congressional committee,
they're not subject to the Freedom of
Information Act. Because in its infinite
wisdom, Congress exempts itself from all
of the laws that it passes.
>> Convenient.
>> Yeah.
And so, I said, uh
I said, "Listen, just off the top of my
head,
I think your only
strategy here is to go public.
That's it. Go public, scream it from the
rooftops, and say you're going to raise
hell on the floor of the Senate every
single day until they open that box."
So, the way we left it was he was going
to think about it.
>> Yeah.
Why would an agency allow a hard copy
like that to exist?
>> Right?
>> I mean,
it's like, "Guys, here's what we're
going to do. We'll print out everything.
Put it in this box.
>> Yeah. And just And just hope nobody ever
finds it.
>> No, it's like And again, I'm not trying
to give anybody like policy approaches
here, but it's like,
you know, there's there's some truth to
the you know, the only way you can keep
a secret between three people is if two
of them are dead.
>> Exactly. Why would you have a written
hard copy if like if somebody in charge
somewhere is like, "This has to be
destroyed." Well, then go [__]
destroy it.
>> Well, you've heard the story about Dick
Helms and MK Ultra.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
Senator Church told him, "Do not destroy
the documents." And he went back to
headquarters from that meeting and said,
"Destroy all the documents."
>> [laughter]
>> He understood the assignment.
>> And yeah, and they fined him like $100.
And everybody was chipping in a buck,
two bucks in the hallway to pay the
director's congressional fine. But
that's why we only have 15% of the MK
Ultra documents because the agency
destroyed everything.
>> Well, there's definitely nothing good in
that other 85%.
>> Yeah, for sure. You know, the reason I
asked you the question about the agency
corrupting itself as I started looking
at, you know, just publicly disclosed
like MI5, MI6.
>> Mhm.
>> Um just any intelligence agency
that you know, we ask people in
countries ask people your job is to lie,
cheat, steal, win at all costs.
And people get really, really, really
good at that. And over enough time, it
seems like and the charter of the CIA to
my understanding is to be externally
focused.
But even when I was just looking at it
this morning, MI5 and MI6, you see the
same similarities.
Those incredible tools of what are
supposed to be external protection
start getting oriented inward. And once
that starts, how do you correct that?
>> Yeah, right. It could take a generation
to correct that. In
>> possible in a generation? Is it is it
>> In In our case, no.
>> gets so corrupted and politicized
and it's like I I believe the CIA, we
need an entity like that. But how do we
fix the entity that we have without
burning it to the ground and losing that
capability?
>> I'm not sure it's possible.
>> Well, you would know more than I would.
I mean, I my access to information comes
from a Google.
>> Right. You know, what what really
wrecked it for us was 9/11
and passage of the Patriot Act.
So,
you know, right now
>> Great branding, by the way.